Paul David Wilkin Papers Relating to Education in the North Western Province of Zambia
Paul David Wilkin Papers Relating to Education in the North Western Province of Zambia
1953-1979
Wilkin, Paul David.
1.25 linear ft.
Transcripts of interviews with various Zambian and English individuals involved in education; photocopies of giovernment records and files from the Ministry of Education, Regional Headquarters, Solwezi.
2614807
Biographical History
Paul David Wilkin graduated from Case Western Reserve University in 1962. From 1963-1965 he was a Fulbright teacher in Zambia, becoming the first headmaster of Balovale (now Zambezi) Secondary School. He spent a year (1966-1967) at the Kenya National Archives as an associate archivist, sponsored by Syracuse University, and then took a position with the University of Zambia (UNZA), where he was a lecturer (Assistant Professor) in the School of Education from 1971-1975 at their main campus in Lusaka. Then from 1975-1979, under the auspices of the Department of Continuing Education, he opened and ran a UNZA center in Solwezi for the entire North Western Province (NWP) of Zambia.
In 1979 Wilkin returned to the United States to work towards his PhD at Syracuse University, which he completed in 1984. After this, he shifted his focus to computer instructional design and training, doing work for (among others) Chase Manhattan Bank and the New York Department of Information Technology (DOITT). From 1986-2001 he worked for Merrill Lynch in their desktop publishing/graphics center, handling introduction of and training on new software applications. During much of this same period he served as a consultant and project manager for Child and Adolescent Psychiatry at the Research Foundation for Mental Hygiene, which is affiliated with Columbia University. In 2001 he joined the staff full time and assists in epidemiological research.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Paul David Wilkin Papers Relating to Education in the North Western Province of Zambia consists of interviews and other material collected by Wilkin while in Zambia as a teacher. Wilkins' goal was to investigate the history of the country and in particular the North Western Province (NWP). According to Wilkin:
"My academic research on the history of Zambia and the NWP was meant as basic historical research...I had initially intended to end my dissertation in 1964, but...[instead] ended it in 1945. Thus many of these oral interviews and other material that focus on the period 1945-1964 were not fully utilized. They now await use by a new generation of scholars." [Letter from the donor, July 2006]
Overview materials contains Wilkin's biographical sketch and an explanation of his connection with the North West Province (NWP). Also included here are a complete list of interviewees, listed several ways, and copies of interview questionnaires.
Interviews and related documents contains transcripts of interviews conducted by Wilkin from 1976-1979. For some interviews, the original audio recordings are also included.
Related documents consist of a small amount of correspondence, a manuscript by and correspondence with John "Ginger" Wright, a folder of material from the Mutanda Mission in Solwezi District, and one folder of material from Wimbledon at the British headquarters of the Africa Evangelical Fellowship (AEF). AEF was formerly known as the South African General Mission (SAGM).
Ministry of Education, Solwezi contains photocopies of government records and files from the Ministry of Education, Regional Headquarters, Solwezi. According to Wilkin's notes that accompany the material, "As of mid-1979, the repository consisted of government records and files stored in an old shed. The files start in 1954, when the NWP was permanently severed from the old Western (now Copperbelt) Province...the original order of these files is impossible to discern." The first folder includes a very detailed listing of all files, cross-referenced where possible with the original file numbers.
Arrangement of the Collection
The material is in the order as provided by the donor. As far as possible, all folder titles are as provided by the donor; titles or additional information provided by the processor are enclosed in square brackets [ ].
Related Material
has a large number of collections relating to adult and continuing education generally. Please refer to for a complete listing. See also the
David Wilkin / Muriel Williams Sanderson Correspondence
for additional Wilkin material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Wilkin, Paul David.; University of Zambia. -- Centre for Continuing Education.; University of Zambia. -- Deptartment of Education.; Continuing education -- Zambia.; Education -- Zambia.; Kabompo District (Zambia); Kasempa District (Zambia); Mwinilunga District (Zambia); North-Western Province (Zambia); Solwezi District (Zambia); Zambia -- History -- 1924-1953.; Zambia -- History -- 1953-1964.; Zambezi District (Zambia); Correspondence.; CD-ROMs.; Diaries.; Interviews.; Manuscripts (document genre); Research notes.; Transcripts.; Educators.; Historians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Paul David Wilkin, 2008, 2010.
Inventory
- Overview materials
  - [PDFs of material in the collection], wilkin_pd_001; accompanied by file listing provided by donor; CD (Box 1)
  - Paul David Wilkin's biographical sketch and connection with the NWP, 1963-1984 (Box 1)
  - Interviewees listed several ways and Interview questionnaires used in the mid-1970s (Box 1)
- Interviews and related documents
  - [NWP/Zambia Interviews]
    - [Chizawu] Interview with Mr. Chifuanyisa Silas Chizawu, 1976 (Box 1)
    - [Forman] Interview with Ms. Janetta Forman, 12 Jan 1976 (Box 1)
    - [Kalepa] Interview with Mr. Remus Kalepa, 23 Feb 1978; 7 Mar 1978 (Box 1)
    - [Kibolya] Interview with Mr. Tito Kibolya, 10 Nov 1977 (Box 1)
    - [Letchford] Interview with Mr. Peter Letchford, 21 Nov 1975 (Box 1)
    - Interview with Rev. Peter Letchford in Albany, NY, 21 Nov 1975; wilkin_pd_002; 2 WAV files; CD (Box 1)
    - [Manuwele] Interview with Mr. Sachilombo Manuwele, Jun 1976 (Box 1)
    - [Mujatulanga] Interview with Mr. Lubinga Mujatulanga, 12 Nov 1978 (Box 1)
    - [Mukimwa] Interview with Mr. David Mukimwa, 12 Nov 1978 (Box 1)
    - [Mutembu] Interview with Mr. Kangasa Mutembu, 7 Dec 1976 (Box 1)
    - [Mutwale] Interview with Mr. M.E. Mutwale, 14 Nov 1978 (Box 1)
    - Interview with Mr. E. Mutwale; part of Interview with Mr. S. Manuwele, 11 Jun 1976; 14 Nov 1978; wilkin_pd_003; 2 WAV files; CD (Box 1)
    - [Mwondela] Interview with Mr. John Mwondela, 8 Jan 1979; 24 Mar 1979; includes photograph (Box 1)
    - Interview with Mr. John Mwondela in Lusaka, Zambia, 8 Jan 1979; wilkin_pd_004; 2 WAV files; CD (Box 1)
    - [Ngalande] Interview with Mr. Aaron Ngalande, 14 Nov 1978; 20 May 1979; 3 WAV files (Box 1)
    - Interviews with Mr. Aaron Ngalande in Kasempa, Zambia, 14 Nov 1978; 20 May 1979; wilkin_pd_005; 2 WAV files; CD (Box 1)
    - [Nisbet] Interview with Alexander and Marjorie Nisbet, 10-11 Jan 1976; 1-2 Apr 1978 (Box 1)
    - [Riddell] Interview with Ms. Agnes Riddell, 7 Dec 1976 (Box 1)
    - [Sameta] Interview with Mr. Silas Sameta, 4 Aug 1976 (Box 1)
    - Interview with Mr. Silas N. Sameta in Kasempa, Zambia, 4 Aug 1976; wilkin_pd_006; 2 WAV files; CD (Box 1)
    - [Sangambo] Interview with Mr. Moses Sangambo, 23 Jul 1977; 26 Jul 1977 (Box 1)
    - [Sayila] Interview with Mr. Peter Sayila, 17 Nov 1976 (Box 1)
    - Interview with Mr. Peter Sayila in Manyinga, Zambia, 17 Nov 1976; wilkin_pd_007; 2 WAV files; CD (Box 1)
    - [Suckling] Interview with Mr. Gordon Suckling, 26 Nov 1977 (Box 1)
    - [Tepa] Interview with Mr. Stanley Tepa, 6 Dec 1976 (Box 1)
    - [Yamba] Interview with Mr. Luka Yamba, 8 Jul 1979 (Box 1)
    - Interview with Mr. Luka Yamba in Solwezi, Zambia, 8 Jul 1979; wilkin_pd_008; 2 WAV files; CD (Box 1)
  - SAGM/AEF Archives interviews
    - [Pirouet] Interview with Mrs. Florence Pirouet, by SAGM in England, undated (Box 1)
    - [Shoosmith] Interview with Mrs. Edith Shoosmith, by SAGM in England, undated (Box 1)
  - Related documents
    - [Misc.] Other conversations / corres.: P.D. Wilkin and individuals re: the NWP, mainly 1970s, 1980s (Box 1)
    - [Short] Correspondence between Robin Short and David Wilkin, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - [Wright] Manuscript by and corres. with John (Ginger) Wright, 1970s (Box 1)
    - Mutanda Mission (NWP) and Wimbledon, England (AEF): Detailed list of archival materials (Box 2)
    - Mutanda Mission (Solwezi Dist): Minutes / Diary / Reports re: education, 1934-1952 (Box 2)
    - Wimbledon Archival Materials: Corres. files re: N. Rh. [Northern Rhodesia?] and Angola, esp. education, 1910-1928 (Box 2)
- Ministry of Education, Solwezi
  - Detailed listing of file contents, 1954-1964 (Box 2)
  - General provincial materials, Provincial Education Officer, general managers, policy and organization, planning, publications (Box 2)
  - Minutes of District Education Authority (DEA), Provincial Education Authority (PEA) and Provincial Teachers Supervisory Council (PTSC), 1953-1964; includes Solwezi, Balovale, Kasempa, Mwinilunga, and Kabompo districts; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Statistics, general, 1958-1964; policy and organizations statistics for Mwinilunga; primary school statistics; general statistics (Box 2)
  - Tour reports, 1953-1964; provincial; Mwinilunga; Manager of Balovale West (Box 2)
  - Secondary schools and trade schools, 1954-1964; Solwezi Secondary School; Balovale Trades School; Trades School, general; Balovale Trades School Council (Box 2)
  - Solwezi District, 1953-1963; general correspondence with mission agencies and local government officials (Box 3)
  - Mwinilunga District, 1954-1965; general correspondence with mission agencies and local government officials (Box 3)
  - Kasempa District, 1954-1965; general correspondence with mission agencies and local government officials (Box 3)
  - Kabompo District, 1954-1964; general correspondence with mission agencies and local government officials (Box 3)
  - Balovale District, general correspondence with mission agencies and local government officials (Box 3)